20 It was a lovely night, so warm that he
threw his coat over his arm and did not even put his silk scarf around his
throat. As he strolled home, smoking his cigarette, two young men in evening dress
passed him. He heard one of them whisper to the other, “That is Dorian Gray.” He
remembered how pleased he used to be when he was pointed out, or stared at, or
talked about. He was tired of hearing his own name now. Half the charm of the
little village where he had been so often lately was that no one knew who he
was. He had often told the girl whom he had lured to love him that he was poor,
and she had believed him. He had told her once that he was wicked, and she had
laughed at him and answered that wicked people were always very old and very
ugly. What a laugh she had!— !—just like a thrush singing. And how pretty she had
been in her cotton dresses and her large hats! She knew nothing, but she had
everything that he had lost. When he reached home, he found his
servant waiting up for him. He sent him to bed, and threw himself down on the
sofa in the library, and began to think over some of the things that Lord Henry
had said to him. Was it really true that one could never
change? He felt a wild longing for the unstained purity of his boyhood— —his robe
white boyhood, as Lord Henry had once called it. He knew that he had tarnished
himself, filled his mind with corruption and given horror to his fancy; that he
had been an evil influence to others, and had experienced a terrible joy in being
so; and that of the lives that had crossed his own, it had been the fairest
and the most full of promise that he had brought to shame. But was it all
irretrievable? Was there no hope for him?
Ah! in what a monstrous moment of pride and passion he had prayed that the
portrait should bear the burden of his days, and he keep the unsullied Splendor
of eternal youth! All his failure had been due to that. Better for him that
each sin of his life had brought its sure swift penalty along with it. There was purification in
punishment. Not “Forgive us our sins” but “Smite us for our iniquities” should be
the prayer of man to a most just God. The curiously carved mirror that
Lord Henry had given to him, so many years ago now, was standing on the table,
and the wh limed Cupids laughed round it as of
old. He took it up, as he had done on that
night of horror when he had first noted the change in the fatal picture, and with
wild tear dimmed eyes looked into its polished shield. Once someone who had
terribly loved him had written to him a mad letter, ending with these idolatrous
words: “The world is changed because you are made of ivory and gold. The curves of
your lips rewrite history.” The phrases came back to his memory, and he repeated them over and
over to himself. Then he loathed his own beauty, and flinging the mirror on the
floor, crushed it into silver splinters beneath his heel. It was his beauty that
had ruined him, his beauty and the youth that he had prayed for. But for those two
things, his life might have been free from stain. His beauty had been to him
but a mask, his youth but a mockery. What was youth at best? A green,
an unripe time, a time of shallow moods, and sickly thoughts. Why had he worn its
livery? Youth had spoiled him. It was better not to think of the past. Nothing
could alter that. It was of himself, and of his own future,
that he had to think. James vain was hidden in a nameless grave in Selby
churchyard. Alan Campbell had shot himself one night in his laboratory, but had not revealed the
secret that he had been forced to know. The excitement, such as it was, over
Basil hallwoods disappearance would soon pass away. It was already waning. He was
perfectly safe there. Nor, indeed, was it the death of Basil hallwood that weighed
most upon his mind. It was the living death of his own soul that troubled him.
Basil had painted the portrait that had marred his life. He could not forgive him
that. It was the portrait that had done everything. Basil had said things to him that were
unbearable, and that he had yet borne with patience. The murder had been simply the madness of a
moment. As for Alan Campbell, his suicide had been his own act. He had chosen to do
it. It was not nothing to him. A new life! That was what he wanted.
That was what he was waiting for. Surely he had begun it already. He had spared
one innocent thing, at any rate. He would never again tempt innocence. He would be
good. As he thought of heti Merton, he began to wonder if the portrait in the
locked room had changed. Surely it was not still so horrible as it had been?
Perhaps if his life became pure, he would be able to expel every sign of evil
passion from the face. Perhaps the signs of evil had already gone away. He would
go and look. He took the lamp from the table and crept upstairs. As he unbar the
door, a smile of joy flitted across his strangely youngl looking face and
lingered for a moment about his lips. Yes, he would be good, and the
hideous thing that he had hidden away would no longer be a terror to him. He
felt as if the load had been lifted from from him already. He went in quietly, locking the
door behind him, as was his custom, and dragged the purple hanging from the
portrait. A cry of pain and indignation broke from him. He could see no change,
save that in the eyes there was a look of cunning and in the mouth the curved
wrinkle of the hypocrite. The thing was still loathsome—
—more loathsome, if possible, than before— —and the scarlet dew that spotted the
hand seemed brighter, and more like blood newly spilled. Then he
trembled. Had it been merely vanity that had made him do his one good deed? Or the
desire for a new sensation, as Lord Henry had hinted, with his mocking laugh? Or
that passion to act a part that sometimes makes us do things finer than
we are ourselves? Or, perhaps, all these?
And why was the red stain larger than it had been? It seemed to have crept like a
horrible disease over the wrinkled fingers. There was blood on the painted
feet, as though the thing had dripped— —blood even on the hand that had not held the knife.
Confess? Did it mean that he was to confess? To give himself up and be put to
death? He laughed. He felt that the idea was monstrous. Besides, even if he did
confess, who would believe him? There was no trace of the murdered man anywhere.
Everything belonging to him had been destroyed. He himself had burned what had
been below stairs The world would simply say that he was mad. They would shut him
up if he persisted in his story.... Yet it was his duty to confess, to suffer public
shame, and to make public atonement. There was a God who called upon men to tell
their sins to earth as well as to heaven.
Nothing that he could do would cleanse him till he had told his own sin. His sin?
He shrugged his shoulders. The de of Basil hallwood seemed very little to him.
He was thinking of heti Merton. For it was an unjust mirror, this
mirror of his soul that he was looking at. Vanity?
Curiosity?
Hypocrisy? Had there been nothing more in his renunciation than that? There had
been something more. At least he thought so. But who could
tell? No. There had been nothing more.
Through vanity he had spared her. In hypocrisy he had worn the mask of
goodness. For curiosity’s sake he had tried the denial of self. He recognized that
now. But this murder— —was it to dog him all his life? Was he always to be
burdened by his past? Was he really to confess?
Never. There was only one bit of evidence left against him. The picture itself— —that
was evidence. He would destroy it. Why had he kept it so long? Once it had given him
pleasure to watch it changing and growing old. Of late he had felt no such
pleasure. It had kept him awake at night.
When he had been away he'd been filled with terror lest other eyes should look
upon it. It had brought melancholy across his passions. Its mere memory had marred
many moments of joy. It had been like conscience to him. Yes, it had been
conscience. He would destroy it.
He looked round and saw the knife that had stabbed Basil hallwood He had cleaned it many times,
till there was no stain left upon it. It was bright, and
glistened. As it had killed the painter, so it would kill the painter’s work, and
all that that meant. It would kill the past, and when that was dead, he would be
free. It would kill this monstrous Soul life and without its hideous warnings, he
would be at peace.
He seized the thing, and stabbed the picture with it. There was a cry heard,
and a crash. The cry was so horrible in its agony that the frightened servants
woke and crept out of their rooms. Two gentlemen, who were passing in the square
below, stopped and looked up at the great house. They walked on till they met a
policeman and brought him back. The man rang the bell several times, but there
was no answer. Except for a light in one of the top windows, the house was was all
dark. After a time, he went away and stood in an adjoining portico and
watched. “Whose house is that, Constable?” asked the elder of the two
gentlemen. “Mr. Dorian gr sir,” answered the policeman. They looked at each other, as
they walked away, and sneered. One of them was Sir Henry Ashton’s uncle. Inside, in
the servants’ part of the house, the half-clad domestics were talking in low
whispers to each other. Old Mrs. Leaf was crying and ringing her hands. Francis was
as pale as death. After about a quarter of an hour, he got the coachman and one
of the footmen and crept upstairs. They knocked, but there was no reply. They called
out. Everything was still. Finally, after vainly trying to force the door, they got
on the roof and dropped down onto the balcony. The windows yielded easily— —their bolts were
old. When they entered, they found hanging upon the wall a splendid portrait of
their master as they had last seen him, in all the wonder of his exquisite youth
and beauty. Lying on the floor was a dead man, in evening dress, with a knife in his
heart. He was withered, wrinkled, and loathsome of visage. It was not till they
had examined the rings that they recognized who it was. THE END
thank you for listening if you like our recordings consider liking this video
and subscribing to our channel so YOU